[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi.
I'm Adam Porter, and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
The other kind of user notification that
we'll talk about
in this lesson are notifications that
appear in the notification area.
And as I said earlier, this kind of
user notification appears in the system
controlled area,
at the top of the device, called the
notification area or the
status bar.
Applications and the android system itself
can use this area to inform users about
the occurrence of various events.
The notification area also provides a user
interface element called a drawer.
And the user can pull down on the
notification
area to open the drawer.
And once it's open, you can see additional
information about
the various notifications that have been
placed in the notification area.
Let's see an example of how these
notifications are used in Android.
So here's my device.
And I'll open up the phone application.
And now I'll start dialing a phone number.
And now, I'll hit the dial button.
And the phone will start dialing the
number, and connecting the phone call.
Now let's say that in the middle of this
phone
call I need to get some information off
the internet.
So, I hit the home button to go back to my
home
screen, and from there I'll open up the
browser application and now
notice up at the top left of my device a
new icon has appeared.
That's a notification.
When I backed out of the phone
application, Android created
this notification object, and put it in
the notification area.
And this notification serves as a reminder
to me that the
phone call is still connected, and it also
serves as a way
for me to quickly return to that phone
call.
Now, back in the browser, I'll go to
www.google.com and I'll execute a search.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's assume at this point I'm armed with
the information that
I needed and I want to go back to my phone
call.
So now, I'll pull down on the notification
area to open the notification drawer.
And once it's open, I can see a
view, which shows me some information
about the call.
And, it allows me to either reconnect to
the call, or to hang up.
Now in this case I want to continue the
call, so I'll click on the notification
area.
And that brings up the phone application,
brings it back
in to the foreground, and allows me to
keep talking.
When you want to send the notification,
there
are several things that you need to
consider.
First, there's the basic notification
itself, which must have at least
text for its title and content, and also a
small icon.
When the notification is sent, it will
eventually arrive in
the notification area where the small icon
will be displayed.
Additionally,
you can set the notifications ticker text,
in which case that text will
also be displayed when the notification
first appears in the notification area.
Finally, if the user opens a notification
drawer, there's a view that they'll see.
Now, by default, this includes the title,
the
detail or content of text, the small icon,
and a time stamp.
You'll also need to define any action that
will occur
should the user click on the notification
draw, drawer view.
Now once you've created the notification,
you may want to
send it, update it, cancel it, or things
like that.
These operations are managed by an
Android system service called the
notification manager.
So let's take a look at two applications
that send notifications, and then
we'll look at some source code to see how
all of this is implemented.
So here, I'll open the notification status
bar application.
And its user interface displays a single
button, labeled Notify.
When I click this button, a notification
will be created and sent, and
it will eventually appear in the
notification area at the top of the phone.
So, let me click on the button now.
[SOUND] And the notification is now
arriving.
And that rooster crowing you hear is
the sound that I attached to that
notification.
You can also see the ticker text scrolling
up in the notification area.
Now after the ticker text finishes
scrolling it will go away and the
notifications icon will remain visible.
So, now I'll open the notification drawer.
You can see the drawer view showing the
icon, the notification title
text, the notification detail text, which
shows the number one
in parentheses, indicating that the notify
button has been pressed one time.
And finally, there's also a time stamp.
Now at this point, I'll just close the
notification drawer, and go
back, and hit the notify button one more
time.
[SOUND]
Now I'll open the notification drawer one
more time.
And you can see that detailed text has
been updated to show
that this is the second time that the
notify button has been pressed.
At this point, I'll click on the
notification, and
you can see that a new activity has
started,
printing out the words Got The Intent.
And the point here, of course, is that you
can
attach an intent to the notification
drawer view in order
to bring the user to the application that
should handle
whatever follow on action that
notification was intended to provoke.
Lets look at a second application.
Notification status bar with custom view.
This application does the same thing as
the last example.
However, it shows a custom view when the
notification drawer is opened.
Now, I'll start the application and hit
the Notify button just like before.
The notification is created and eventually
appears [SOUND] in the notification area.
However, when I open the notification
drawer, I'm not going to see the standard
view, I'll see my own custom view.
Let me open the notification drawer now.
And, there's our eyeball, and the words,
You've Been Notified, with the number in
parenthesis.
Now I'll close the drawer, and I'll hit
the Notify button again.
[SOUND]
I'll open the drawer again and you can
see that everything's same, except that
the number one
has become the number two to show that
this
is the second notification, which updated
the first one.
And finally, I'll click on the
notification drawer view, which
starts up a new activity displaying the
words, Got The Intent.
Okay.
So let's look at the
code for that second application
NotificationStatusBarWithCustomView.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And here I'm back in the IDE, and I'll
open the application's main activity.
Starting at the top, this code creates an
ID
for the notification that's, that it's
going to send.
And this allows the notification manager
to
update this notification after it's first
been sent.
And next there's some variables that hold
the text elements of the notification,
including it's ticker text, title, and
content.
After that, the code sets up some
information that is used to
play a sound and to vibrate the device
when this notification arrives.
Next, the code creates the custom view
that will be displayed in the notification
drawer.
The layout for that view is in
the custom_notification.xml file.
Let's take a look at that.
As you can see this view is a linear
layout with two child views.
One is an image view, the one that
displays
the eyeball, and the other is a text view.
And it displays the text you've been
notified.
Back in the main activity, let's look at
the onCreate method.
And here the code creates an intent called
M notification intent.
This intent will explicitly activate the
notification subactivity.
The next line of code is something that we
haven't talked about before.
This line
creates something called a pending intent.
Based on the M notification intent that
was created on the previous line.
A pending an intent is essentially a
permission slip that allows
one piece of code to stand in for another
piece of code.
And what I mean by that, is that this
permission
slip allows the second piece of code to
activate the underlying
intent, as if it were the first piece of
code.
And that is, it does it with its, the
permissions and the identity of that first
piece of code.
So moving on.
The notify button's listener first updates
the content text.
To indicate the number of times the
button's been pressed.
Then it constructs the actual notification
using
the notification.builder class.
The code makes a new
notification.builder object, and then it
sets the ticker
text, sets the small icon, and then sets
auto-cancel to true.
Now this tells Android to cancel the
notification
if the user clicks on the drawer view.
Next, it sets the content intent, and
this is the pending intent that defines
the action
to take when the user clicks on the drawer
view.
Next, it sets the sound and vibration
patterns that should play when the
notification arrives.
And lastly, it sets the custom view that
should be displayed when the user
pulls down on the notification drawer.
Now, the notification is set up,
the code then gets a reference to the
notification manager by calling
getSystemService passing in the ID of the
notification service.
And finally, the code calls notify on the
notification manager passing in the ID of
the notification.
Which allows existing notifications to be
updated, and it also
passes in the result of calling build on
the notification.builder object.
And that build method is what actually
generates the actual notification object.
So that's all for our lesson on user
notifications.
Please join me next time when we'll
discuss the BroadcastReceiver class.
See you then.
[BLANK_AUDIO]