[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi I'm Adam Porter, and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
In this lesson, we're going to talk about
notifications.
Notifications are basically messages,
sometimes quite rich, that
applications show to users, outside the
normal user interface of
the application.
For example, suppose you have an
application that
can download an eBook from over the
internet.
In that case, you probably want to let the
user select
a book to download, but then continue to
use the application.
Or even exit it altogether while the book
is downloading.
And if so, you probably also want to let
the user know
when the download finishes.
And if it was successful.
To do that, you need to do a few things.
You need to figure out when the download
finishes.
And then you need to display some kind of
message to give the user that information.
In this lesson, I'll talk about two
different kinds of user notifications that
Android supports.
The first kind are
toast messages, which, I suppose, get
their name from
the fact that they pop up on the screen.
We've actually already seen toast messages
many times in previous lessons.
For example, we've used them quite a
bit to demonstrate that something was
happening.
Whenever we pressed a button.
The second kind are notification area or
status bar notifications.
These notifications are visible and can be
accessed in the
system controlled notification area at the
top of the device.
And again, we've already seen examples of
this.
For instance in the applications
fundamentals lesson, I showed
how a device was receiving an incoming MMS
message.
And you might remember, that when the MMS
message actually arrived,
an icon appeared at the top left of the
phone.
And the user could then pull down on the
notification
area to expose more information about that
incoming MMS message.
Okay, so let's recap this.
Android provides several different kinds
of user notifications.
And these notifications are messages to
the user
that are sent on an as needed basis.
And that appear outside the normal user
interface of the application.
So an edit text view in which you type an
MMS message, or the button that you
hit to send the resulting SMS message,
both of
which are always visible, when you compose
the message.
Those are not user notifications.
But a message that pops
up a few seconds after you hit the send
button.
That tells you for example that the
message was sent successfully.
Or an icon that appears at the top of your
device, indicating that an
MMS message has arrived, even though
you're
currently reading a webpage with a browser
application.
Those things are user notifications and
those are
the things that we're going to talk about
today.
Now, some Android
user notifications exist to provide
feedback to
the user about something that they're
doing.
And one such mechanism are the toast
messages that we talked about.
Another are dialogs.
Now, we went over dialogs in a quite a bit
of detail during the
lesson on user interface classes, so I'm
not going to talk about dialogs in this
lesson.
Another kind of user notification
are the notification area notifications.
And these are typically used to announce
unpredictable
events to the user, and to do it
in a way that doesn't interrupt whatever
else
they happen to be doing at that moment.
And again, think of the incoming SMS
message situation.
Putting an icon in the notification area
tells you that a message has arrived.
But it doesn't do
it in an obtrusive or peremptory way.
The message is there, and you're free to
deal with it.
Whenever it's convenient for you.
Toast messages, as you've seen, are
temporary
messages that pop up on the display.
For instance, to let the user know that an
operation has completed successfully.
Toasts automatically fade in, and fade out
of view.
And their job is to provide information to
the user, but they're not
meant to gather information that's
going to
get sent back to the hosting application.
You can create Toast messages using the
Toast classes' make text method.
That method takes a couple parameters,
including the text that you want to
display and the amount of time over which
you want that text, to be visible.
And after you've created the toast, you
can then display it,
by calling the show method, on the toast
you've just created.
So, let's take a look at an example
application, that uses, toast messages.
Here I'm starting up a notification toast
application.
This application displays a single button,
labeled show toast
which is exactly what it'll do when I
press it.
So I'll press that button now.
And there, near the bottom of the screen,
you
see a small pop-up window that says,
you're toast.
Now,
if we open up the application source code
in the ID, we'll see how this is
implemented.
Here I'm highlighting button listener for
the Show Toast button.
Inside, you see a call to the make text
method.
Passing in the text and passing in the
constant toast.length_long.
Which ends up making the text visible for
about three and a half seconds.
And at the end of that line there's a
call to the show method that actually
displays the Toast.
Now, if you want a fancier Toast message,
you
an also create a custom view for your
Toast.
For example, you can create a custom
layout in XML, inflate it and attach
the inflated view to the Toast message
with a call to the set view method.
Let's see an example.
So, here's my device.
And
now I'll start up the notification, Toast,
with custom view application.
Like the simple toast example, this
application displays one button labeled
Show Toast.
And I can press that button to display the
Toast message.
In this case however, when I do press the
button; you'll see a
custom toast view rather than the simple
grey pop up that we saw before.
So here we go.
And there's your custom Toast message.
With a text, Your Toast, and an extra
eyeball to help drive home the message.
So
let's open up the main activity for this
application.
And look at how we created the Toast
message.
Now, as you can see, when the show Toast
button is pressed.
The code first creates a new Toast object.
The next two lines set
the location of the Toast on the display.
And specify the length of time
for which it will be visible.
Then there's a call to set view, in which
the first parameter is the result of
inflating the XML layout that's in the
custom_toast.xml file.
Let's open that file.
Now here you can see that the custom
view is a relative layout containing two
children.
The first child is the image view that
holds the eye ball.
The second child is a text view that
displays the text, you're toast.
And then, back in the main activity,
there's a final
line that calls the show method to display
the toast.
[BLANK_AUDIO]