[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi.
I'm Adam Porter, and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
In this lesson, we're going to talk about
another fundamental Android component: the
BroadcastReceiver class.
I'll begin by discussing the
BroadcastReceiver class, and the
basic workflow that you'll follow when
you're using it.
Next, I'll discuss how broadcast receivers
are registered with the Android system.
After that,
I'll talk about the different ways that
events can be broadcast to those broadcast
receivers.
And lastly, I'll finish up with a short
discussion of how
broadcast receivers are notified and how
they handle the broadcasts they receive.
The BroadcastReceiver is a base class for
components whose purpose is to wait for
certain events to occur, to receive those
events, and then to react to them.
And the way this all works is that
individual broadcast
receivers register to receive the specific
events in which they're interested.
For example, there's a broadcast receiver
in Android
whose job is to listen for outgoing MMS
messages.
Now, somewhere else at a later time, a
component
does something that it wants to inform
broadcast receivers about.
So it creates an intent that represents
that event, and then it
broadcasts that intent.
So, there are other components in android
that prepare MMS messages so that they can
be later sent out over the network.
Once the MMS message is ready, then
there's
a component that creates an
action_send_message intent, and
then broadcasts that intent.
Android then takes the intent that was
just broadcast and delivers it to that
component
we talked about before that has registered
to receive action underscore send
underscore message intents.
And that component finally receives the
intent by getting
a call to its onReceive method, with that
intent as
one of the parameters to the method.
Now for our MMS example, the
component receives the action_send_message
intent and
eventually sets off a service to deliver
the MMS message.
So to recap, the basic workflow is
one, broadcast receivers register to
receive specific intents.
Two, some component generates an intent
and then broadcasts it to the system.
Three, Android delivers that intent to the
broadcast receivers that registered to
receive it.
And four, the broadcast receivers then get
a call to their onReceive method during
which they handle the incoming event.
So, let's talk about
each of these steps one at a time.
So in order to register a broadcast
receiver developers have two options.
One, they can register the broadcast
receiver statically by putting some
information
in the AndroidManifest.XML file of the
application to which the broadcast
receiver belongs.
Or two, they can register the broadcast
receiver
dynamically by in invoking some methods at
run time.
So to register a broadcast receiver
statically you add a receiver tag
in your applications AndroidManifest.XML
file, and then
within that receiver tag you put at least
one intent filter tag.
And the information there tells Android
that when
an intent matching this intent filter is
broadcast,
this broadcast receiver wants to know
about it.
And the format for a receiver tag looks
something like this.
You start with the receiver keyword, and
then you add some of the following
attributes.
And some of those attributes, include
Android enabled, which
allows you to enable or disable a
particular receiver.
Another is android:exported.
If set to true, then this receiver
can receive broadcasts from outside its
application.
While if it's set to false,
then the receiver can only receive intents
that are broadcast by other components
within this application.
Another attribute in android:name.
Which gives the name of the class that
implements this receiver.
There's also android:permission.
Which defines a permission string that the
sender of an intent must have in
order for this receiver to receive an
intent from them.
And as I said, you'll also have to specify
at least one
intent filter tag, which we covered back
in our lesson on intents.
Now, once you've created the receiver tag,
you insert an intent filter
tag as one of its children, and just like
with intent filters that are used to start
activities these intent filter tags can
specify things like an
action, data, and categories.
Now if you do register a receiver
statically, that information will be read
and
processed when the system boots up.
Or, when the application package is added
if that happens while the system is
running.
So, let's take a look at an application
that's statically registers a single
broadcast receiver to receive a custom
intent
that I'll call the show toast intent.
Here's my device.
And
I'll start up the single broadcast static
registration
application.
This application displays a single button
labeled Broadcast Intent.
Pressing this button causes an
intent to be broadcast and then routed to
and received by
a broadcast receiver, which then displays
a toast message.
Now I'll press the button.
And there you see the toast message
indicating that the receiver got the
intent.
Now here I've opened up the application in
the IDE.
Now I'll open the main activity.
And this code first defines an intent
action string that will be
used to identify this intent.
And scrolling down
there's a button listener that calls the
context.send
broadcast method, passing in an intent and
a permission string.
The intent will be matched against
registered intent filters.
While the permission string indicates that
this intent can only
be delivered to broadcast receivers that
have this particular permission.
You can also register broadcast receivers
programmatically at run time.
For instance, if you want your broadcast
receiver to respond
to intents only while your activity is in
the foreground,
well then you can dynamically register and
unregister them in
your activities on resume and on pause
methods for example.
And to do this, you'll first create an
intent filter object, specify the intents
that you want to register for.
Next, you create the BroadcastReceiver and
then
you register it by calling a
registerReceiver method.
And there are different implementations of
this method.
One is in the LocalBroadcastManager class.
And this one is for broadcasts
that are meant only for this application.
And therefore, they don't need to be
broadcast system wide.
The other implementation is in the Context
class and this one broadcasts intents
system
wide so these intents can potentially be
received by any application on your
device.
And finally, as necessary,
you can call an unRegisterReceiver method
to unregister these
broadcast receivers.
Let's look at the source code for the
single broadcast dynamic registration
application.
This application looks exactly like the
previous application.
There's a broadcast intent button, and
when you press it an intent is broadcast,
a broadcast receiver receives the intent,
and then displays a toast message.
Internally however, its implementation is
a little bit different.
So, this code starts off by creating an
intent action string, and next
it creates an intent filter object with
the just created action string.
After that, it creates a broadcast
receiver instance called receiver.
And then, down in the on create method,
the code gets and instance
of the localBroadcastManager, which as I
said is used to
broadcast and receive intents only within
this application.
Next, the code uses the
localBroadcastManager
to register the receiver object for the
show toast intent.
And after that if the broadcast intent
button is pressed, the listener
calls localBroadcastManager.sendBroadcast
passing in the intent.
When the button is pushed, the
localBroadcastManger
will send the intent to the receiver
object which operates just as it did in
the last application, creating and
displaying a toast message.
Now in my example so far, simply broadcast
a single intent to a single receiver, but
Android supports a variety of different
ways in which intents can be broadcast.
For example, intents can be broadcast
normally or in order.
Normal broadcasts are delivered to
subscribed
broadcast receivers in an undefined order.
So if you have two broadcast receivers
that should receive a single intent it's
possible that both broadcast receivers
could be
processing the intent at the same time.
Ordered broadcasts on the other hand
deliver the intent to multiple
broadcast receivers one at a time in
priority order,
and broadcasts can also be sticky or
non-sticky.
A sticky intent sticks around after its
initial broadcast,
so a broadcast receiver that is registered
after the initial broadcast
of an intent, may still be able to receive
it even
though it wasn't around when the intent
was actually broadcast.
And this feature is useful, for example,
to record system state
changes such as changes in the battery
level or charging status.
In these cases it doesn't matter to the
receiver when the state changed.
Right?
They just want to know what the current
state is.
Non-sticky broadcasts
in contrast are discarded after their
initial broadcast.
And these broadcasts are more suited,
therefore,
to reporting that a certain event has
occurred.
In these cases, if the receiver isn't
registered to receive
the broadcast when it happens, then they
won't get it.
And lastly, as we saw in the examples,
some broadcast
methods also take a permission string,
which limits the
broadcast to those broadcast receivers
that have the specified permission.
Now, if you find yourself having trouble
getting broadcasts to the
right broadcast receivers, there are a few
things that you can do.
One, is to have Android log extra
information about its
intent resolution process.
And you can do this by setting the
flag_debug_log_resolution flag in the
intent that you're going to broadcast.
Another is to use the ADB tool to
find out what broadcast receivers have
been registered.
And you can use the dumpsys command, like
this,
to show broadcast receivers that are
dynamically registered, and you can
use it like this to show those that are
statically registered.